<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Jesuite and priest discovered, or, A Brief discourse of the policies of the Church of Rome, in preserving itself, and dividing of Protestant states and kingdoms in which is plainly demonstrated, the effects of their political operations upon us at this day, in respect to religion, and matters of state : together, with the necessity of their banishment.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1663</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 35 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A46846</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J703</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R39013</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18206236</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 18206236</idno>
            <idno type="VID">107080</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A46846)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 107080)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1125:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Jesuite and priest discovered, or, A Brief discourse of the policies of the Church of Rome, in preserving itself, and dividing of Protestant states and kingdoms in which is plainly demonstrated, the effects of their political operations upon us at this day, in respect to religion, and matters of state : together, with the necessity of their banishment.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1663.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained with print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesuits --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:107080:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE JESUITE AND PRIEST DISCOVERED; <hi>Or,</hi> A Brief DISCOURSE OF The Policies of the Church of ROME, in Preſerving it Self, and Dividing of <hi>Proteſtant</hi> States and Kingdoms.</p>
            <p>In which is plainly Demonſtrated, the Effects of their Political Operations upon Us at this Day, in reſpect to Religion, and matters of State. Together, with the neceſſity of their Baniſhment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed, 1663.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:107080:2"/>
            <head>The Jeſuite Diſcovered.</head>
            <p>THe Policy of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> conſiſteth principally in dividing it Self into Divers and Sundry Orders, which are provided to retain all Humors in Mankind. By this, She maketh Her Intereſt ſtrong and powerfull: and preſerveth Her ſelf from ruine; without which, She could not have continued to this Day, or bin able to act any thing to the hurt or detriment of the reformed Churches.</p>
            <p>Firſt, As to the diverſity of Orders amongſt them; their only Policy to thoſe who deſpiſe the Wealth of the World, and that can content themſelves with Poverty, are the Mendicants; their Prelates abound in Riches, their Hermits and Capuchins for ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity of Life, their Cardinals for Pomp and Glory, their Jeſuits for Learning, and all manner of Sciences; their Popes and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates exerciſing Soveraignty and Princely Command: They take eſpecial care to ingage and raviſh all manner of Humors. On the one ſide of a Street, you ſhall have a Nunnery, or Cloiſter of Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins; on the other ſide a Sty of Courtizans. One day you ſhall have them all in Masks, with all manner of Obſceneneſs and Folly that can be imagined, or the corrupt nature of man deſire; the day following they will be all in Proceſſions, whipping themſelves un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the bloud commeth. On one Door you ſhall have Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, throwing Souls and Bodies to Hell: on another Door, a Jubilee, or full Diſcharge of all Villanies, Murthers, Fornication, Drunkenneſs, Swearing, Forſwearing, Poyſoning; in a word, all manner of ſin, Leudneſs, and Impiety: They were led to this Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy by the hand of Confeſſions; by that means they come to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern the nature of Mankind in general. They do not hold it ſafe to reſtrain any of theſe Humors, leſt it ſhould cauſe Eruptions, and make their Subjects ſeek ſome other way for to vent them in; ſo that theſe Orders are as Sinks to receive the Humors. They have not the ſword of the Spirit to deſtory Vice, nor the Word of Truth to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:107080:3"/>
convince of evil Doing; therefore they muſt truſt to carnal Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy: <hi>For the more growth ſin hath among them, the more the Church in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth in Riches,</hi> for that all puniſhment upon the matter, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons, are <hi>Pecuniary.</hi> The wayes they have to raviſh all ſorts of affections, as is ſaid before, are well nigh infinite, there being not any thing either Sacred or Prophane, no Vertue or Vice almoſt, nothing of how contrary condition ſoever, which the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> maketh not in ſome ſort or other to ſerve Her turn, that each fancy may be ſatisfied, and each appetite find what to feed on. Whatſoever their Wealth can ſway with its Lovers; or volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Poverty with the deſpiſers of the World; what Honour with the Ambitious; what Obedience with the Humble; what great Imployments with ſtirring or Martial ſpirits; as the Orders of Knights, that of <hi>Rhodes,</hi> St. <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> thoſe now of <hi>Malta,</hi> that of the Knights of St. <hi>Morris,</hi> and St. <hi>Lazare</hi> amongſt the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voyards, eſtabliſhed by Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the fourth, 1644. the Knights of the Order of the Dog and Cock in <hi>France.</hi> The firſt were to wear a Collar full of Stags heads, with the Image of a Dog to hang thereon, to ſignify fidelity; theſe followed <hi>Philip</hi> the firſt, King of <hi>France</hi> in his Wars: Thoſe of the Cock, ſignified watchfulneſs, and had a Cock for their Blazon, for that the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients accounted it to be a Bird of <hi>Mars:</hi> The Order of the Knights of the <hi>Ginit</hi> in <hi>France:</hi> The Order of the Knights of the <hi>Leli,</hi> in the Realm of <hi>Navar:</hi> The Order of Knights of St. <hi>Mary</hi> in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> of St. <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Accon,</hi> and of St. <hi>Thomas,</hi> of St. <hi>Saviour</hi> in <hi>Arragon,</hi> Knights of <hi>Mountjoy</hi> in <hi>Syria:</hi> The Order of Knights of the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Virgin in <hi>Italy:</hi> The Order of the Knights of the Golden fleece in the Houſes of <hi>Burgundy</hi> and <hi>Auſtria,</hi> with above 200 more Orders of Knights too large here to be mentioned. Theſe Orders are for their Metall'd and Active ſpirits. Alſo, they have their perpetual proviſions, for their Heavy and Reſtive Bodies in their Cells: What content or pleaſure nature can take in Paſs-Times and Jollities; What contrariwiſe, the Auſtere mind in Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline and Rigor; What Love, either Chaſtity can raiſe in the pure; or Voluptuouſneſs, in the impure or diſſolute: What allurements are in knowledg to draw the Contemplative, or in
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:107080:3"/>
Actions of State to imploy the Polititian: What Miracles with the Credulous: What Viſions with the Fantaſtical: What Ceremonies can do with the Superſtitious: What Prayers with the Devout: What diſpenſing with breach of all Rules, with Men of lawleſs condition: In ſum, whatſoever the Heart of man can deſire, he is fitted with, in the Storehouſe of the Church of <hi>Romes</hi> Politicks; for himſelf to purſue, or at leaſt to Adore or Reverence in another. This is the main Wheel on which the Church moveth, and keepeth faſt Members of all ſorts; ſo that, by this means of providing for the ſeveral Humours of the Members, it enjoyeth the more quiet in it ſelf, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth able to oppoſe and diſturb the Reformed Churches; They have other ſtrings to their Bow, beſides this aforemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, which is indeed the chief. The one is their Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles.</p>
            <p>Another is, their keeping the Laiety in Ignorance.</p>
            <p>For their Miracles: the numbers are infinite that they reckon up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but they are all of the ſame ſtamp and Impreſſion with theſe, <hi>viz.</hi> the repreſentation of the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> with the Babe, their Eyes to move at certain times: it is performed by Engine work, ſecretly contrived to cheat the people into a belief of their Fop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peries: the lifting up the hand of the Image of the Virgin, in imitation of bleſſing the People, and the like. Her Image giving Milk on the Day of the Nativity, conveyed by ſmall Tinn Pipes at a great diſtance, begot the admiration in the people, and an Implicit faith of all theſe wonders. A ſubtil Jeſuite ſhall make his abode five or ſix years more or leſs, being blind (at leaſt ſeem ſo to be) by Dying the inner skin of the Eye, by a water diſtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led from a certain Herb, not fit to be mentioned here; or ſeem Lame, or Leprozed; or otherwiſe by <hi>Guzmonds</hi> Art of raiſing an artificial Leproſy, now uſed among ſome Beggars, to move com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion in the Charitable. When he is well known, he ſhall come and implore the aid of ſuch a Saint: Immediately he ſhall be as whole as a Fiſh, and his ſight ſhall be reſtored; then that Saint is repaired unto far and near; offerings come plentifully; Thus they contrive to enrich the Church, and if it chance that any Bath
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:107080:4"/>
or Spring break forth of the Earth that paſſeth thorow any mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, and is of Phyſical uſe (as all ſuch are) it is Dedicated to one Saint or other; and ſometimes waters of no vertue at all naturally, are cryed up to be for ſuch and ſuch uſes, as the Well or Water of <hi>St. Winifrid,</hi> or the like. People repair to it, to uſe it: the which, together with the opinion that they have of it, doth effect ſome kind of cures. It is a true ſaying, that the Patients good opinion of the Phyſitian or means, is more then half the cure. The Polititians of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> know the truth of that ſaying, therefore they uſe all means poſſible to increaſe the faith of their Patients or Clyents; which maketh their cure more certain and eaſy. It is known to Phyſitians, that ſeveral Diſtempers are cured by the ſtrength of Imagination, as well as ſeveral Natures are ſubjected to ſeveral Diſtempers by Imagination. As in time of Peſtilence; many that would dye of other diſeaſes than what was prepared by the Humors, or Diſorders in nature. The Fear and Imagination of the party diſtempered, is as a mould to caſt the form of the thing feared in: though others do dye of it, being prepared, as tinder is apt matter for fire; ſo they more aptly are ſubject to the Influences operating at that time. God maketh uſe of ſecond means, although that of the Plague be an immediate diſpenſation from Him, and is as it were a thing diſtinct from, and other than, the ordinary workings of Nature.</p>
            <p>The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> are very well acquainted, and do much ſtudy Natural Magick, and are very good Proficients therein, as in many hundred caſes, they may be traced in their Legends; as moſt of all which may be performed by the natural Magical Art, though they aſcribe unto them the honour of Miracles: As for Example, that of St. <hi>Francis,</hi> his great wonder of kindling a fire with Ice. We muſt here let you to know, that it is eaſy for Artiſts to make ſuch a compoſition, that ſo ſoon as one drop of water toucheth it, it ſhall become a violent flame; the which is effected by <hi>Antiperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſis;</hi> that is to ſay, the ſtrengthning and oppoſing any quality againſt its contrary, as of cold againſt heat; it may be repreſented in a more familiar Example, as that of the firing of Corn or Hay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacks, when ſtackt too moiſt or wet; it doth not fire, becauſe of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:107080:4"/>
heat and dryth, but it fireth becauſe too moiſt or cold: which is able to oppoſe, though not overcome the other; qualities being ſtirred, devour the matter that retained them both. Alſo the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is acquainted with Sorcery, or Diabolical Magick; the which, was practiſed by Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the 6th. Who, the Papiſts themſelves cannot deny, but that he gave himſelf to the Devil; who was not only the wickedeſt of Men, but alſo the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edeſt of Popes: He beſtowed the Riches of the Church upon his Baſtards; he made away the Brother of <hi>Bajazet</hi> for a ſum of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, though he fled to him for protection; he uſed his own Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Lucretia,</hi> the Wife to three Princes. Innumerable examples might be given of this nature too large here to be inſiſted upon: So much as to their Miracles, and the means by which they effect them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, As to their other part or branch of their Policy, <hi>viz.</hi> Their practiſe to divide the reformed Churches: they do it by In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments and Emiſſaries of their own, who are ſent to divide and infect them with Errors and Contradictions. They, out of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minaries, of the Order of Jeſu, do ſend uſually great numbers to all Parts to do this work. This Order was wholly Religious before <hi>Luther's</hi> time, they vowed the preaching of the Goſpel to Pagans, and the Inſtructing Chriſtians in good Letters <hi>gratis.</hi> When <hi>Luther</hi> began to oppoſe the power of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> they caſt off their Religious Vows, and betook themſelves to defend the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> to be above general Councils and Princes, by principles and practiſes of Policy, or rather Deviliſh circumventing cunning; for they value not the way or means by which they attain to the accompliſhing of what they undertake. When ſeeming Piety ſhall make way for what they deſign, they have it at their fingers ends; when the moſt impious and wicked Act, that ever was on earth done, muſt accompliſh what they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, they there alſo are moſt ready: But they make choice rather of ſeeming ſanctity, than of wicked Violations; becauſe the Church hath a better ſalve to cure the wounds made by the former, than it hath for the wounds made by the latter.</p>
            <p>The manner of this political Orders Practiſe, you ſhall find in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:107080:5"/>
               <hi>Campanella</hi>'s Diſcourſe, (one of that Order) touching the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Monarchy, <hi>Chap.</hi> 25. He adviſeth the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> in the latter End of the Raign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> in theſe words, <hi>Now as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the weakning of the</hi> Engliſh, <hi>there can no better way poſſibly be found out, than by cauſing diviſion and diſſention amongſt them, and by continual keeping up the ſame; which will quickly furniſh the</hi> Spaniſh <hi>Crown, or the Church with more opportunities and advantages than the power of great Armies can procure or produce: As for the Religion of that people, it is that of</hi> Calvin, <hi>though very much moderated, and not ſo Rigid, and Auſtere as it is at</hi> Geneva; <hi>which yet cannot be ſo eaſily extinguiſhed or rooted out there, unleſs there were ſome certain Schools ſet up in</hi> Flanders, <hi>with which people, the</hi> Engliſh <hi>have great dealing and Commerce: by means of which there ſhould be ſcattered abroad the Seeds of Schiſm and Diviſion, in the natural Sciences; as namely, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the</hi> Stoicks, Peripateticks, <hi>and</hi> Teleſians, <hi>by which the Errour of the</hi> Calviniſts <hi>might be made manifest: For the truth is, That Sect is diametrically contrary to the Rules of Policy; for they teach, that Whether a man do well or ill, he doth all by divine Impulſion; which</hi> Plato <hi>demonſtrates againſt</hi> Homer, <hi>to be oppoſite to all ſounder Policy, which ſayes, That every man hath free Liberty of Will, either to do well or ill; So that it is in our power to do and obſerve whatever is comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and from hence we are to expect our Reward or Puniſhment; accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as I have taught in my Dialogue touching Policy, where I have diſcourſed of this Point, though but briefly; which they, ſince they have become Hereticks, are grown ſomewhat ſubtill in; and yet being of a Nature that is ſtill deſirous of Novelties and Change, they are eaſily wrought over to any thing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here may be diſcerned what advantage they have over us in reſpect of Religion; and the Reader may perceive the Order and Working of theſe Polititians; who lay their Deſigns deep: they ſtudy Men, their Minds, Objects, Cauſes, and their Effects, and the Effects of Effects, <hi>ad infinitum:</hi> They (and they only) have Iulled this Nation into ſo many ſeveral Lethargies and Sleeps; wherein, Thoſe of this perſwaſion dream, they only are in the truth, and all others in Errors; So thoſe of another, do the like of the former.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:107080:5"/>
And thus the Jeſuit hath divided us, by his obſerving the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Humors of the Engliſh Nation; thoſe that are more Auſtere, as the Presbyterian; thoſe that are more pure, as the Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, or ſeparate Churches; the Anabaptiſts, as holy and ſelect, and as perſons ſet apart from the World, by their Submiſſion to that Ordinance of Baptiſm, at years of Diſcretion: The Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence is not much material, yet the Jeſuit maketh uſe of theſe Diſtinctions, to carry on his deſign, by promoting of every one of them, and by keeping them at an eaven poyſe; and ſometimes again ſubdivide, that thereby, whilſt he divideth them that are moſt near to the Truth, he may work the better upon thoſe that are of a baſer Mind and Humor, and that will receive more groſs Principles, more remote from the Truth: And thoſe he practiſeth upon ſuch who have not a ſpirit of diſcerning, but have ſome Affection to devotion, as on the Seeker and the Quaker; more loſer Principles on the Familiſts and Ranters; merrier and pret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty-conceited Devotions amongſt the Roſicrucians, and Pſalteriſts, or Halilujaiſts, or Singers; ſo of many others: But he ſometimes muſt make uſe of Truth, and the wayes of Truth, to gain advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages in his Deſign; as the Devils in the poſſeſſed, ſaid, <hi>What have we to do with thee,</hi> Jeſus <hi>of</hi> Nazareth; <hi>thou Son of the most High God?</hi> The Devil acknowledged Chriſt to be the Son of God, in deſign; for the People ſeeing him to be acknowledged by the Devils, they drew this Concluſion, That he did caſt out Devils by the Power of <hi>Belzebub,</hi> the Prince of Devils: the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils would never have confeſſed, that he was the Son of God, but to produce that contrary Effect: So the Jeſuit doth not promote, or caſt himſelf under, thoſe forms that are true, or near the Truth, to any other end than to produce thoſe contrary Effects before premiſed, <hi>viz.</hi> to divide and ſubdivide, to render the Churches leſſe formidable or powerful in oppoſing the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> if not ſubvert them, and bring them back to the Obedience of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> That this is certain, and not taken up upon conjecture, is evident, by the practiſe of <hi>Thomas Ramſy,</hi> of the order of Jeſus, who joyned with a gathered Church at <hi>Hexam,</hi> in the North of <hi>England,</hi> under this pretence, That he was a
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:107080:6"/>
Jew, and gave himſelf his name, <hi>Joſeph Ben Iſrael;</hi> his particular Inſtructions was to inſinuate the Doctrine of Free-Will, the which he did accompliſh, and carryed on with a High hand, untill he was diſcovered; detected, and caſt into Priſon: One that got more than ordinary advantages of Familiarity, obtained of him the Diſcovery of many ſecrets in the Policy of the Jeſuits practice, ſome of which are theſe; The waies that they practiſe in their Seminaries, to bring up youth, and render them fit for the intended Imployments, they put them upon, are; They, Firſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the <hi>Genius</hi> of the Party, and obſerving the peculiar Gifts he is naturally indowed with, they fit him only for that ſervice; he learneth ſome Trade (to hide and blind his Order,) which he practiſeth; by this means he becometh Eminent amongſt thoſe of that perſwaſion he caſteth himſelf into: and, to put him into ſuch a condition, that he may be freed from the ſtings of Conſcience, they firſt teach him to ſwear, curſe, damn, and forſwear; and immediately to implore the Throne of Grace, with all pious De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion imaginable: By this means they become flexible, and fit for any deſign that lyeth before them to promote; and if Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſtill ſhould purſue them, their Pardons help at a dead lift.</p>
            <p>And this they warrant from that Maxim, That no way is to be refuſed, whereby the Felicity and Peace of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is to be promoted and ſecured: Let it be by any means whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, lawful or unlawful. Theſe things conſidered, How much doth it behoove all that truly fear God, or have any true ſincere Religion in their breaſt, to deteſt and decline the thought of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning this Form, or that; in regard Religion doth not lye in Forms, but in the powerful practiſe of all Holineſſe, and godly Converſation; and therefore conſent to ſome Natural Harmony, or Form neceſſary to the Truth, that the union thereof may be ſuch, as it may be able to make head againſt the Church of <hi>Rome</hi>'s deſigns, and the Projects of the Devil; elſe we ſhall continually be divided and ſubdivided, till at laſt we ſhall neither have form or ſubſtance left, and be hurried into all manner of Confuſion. The Truth of which is to be ſeen at this day amongſt us: How do the giddy and unſtable, run out of one thing into another! The
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:107080:6"/>
Devil and Jeſuit can ſcarcely invent that which hath either ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming Form or Order in it, faſt enough, or ſo faſt, as giddy People, that were never well principl'd in Religion, are ready to be led away captive by poyſonous Notions that are daily diſtilled amongſt them, to the ruine of their own Souls, and to the diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of God: Who, ſo ſoon as they are tainted by thoſe deluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, immediately think themſelves illuminated by Divine Light, as we ſee by ſad Experience at this day amongſt us, by People that yield Obedience, and ſubmit to all manner of Deluſions, and conform to them as Impulſes from on High; which is nothing elſe but the Effects of depraved minds, agitated, illuminated, and acted by the Evil One.</p>
            <p>The Art of the Jeſuits is manifeſt: Another way which ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth them to great purpoſe, is, the looſening of People from Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples; and when effected, diſtill Notions to purſue after the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of new Lights, and inſtead of meeting with that which is Light, they cloſe with what ſuiteth to their corrupt Minds or Ends: The Inferiour ſort of every Perſwaſion, when the Jeſuit hath diſtilled his poyſons amongſt them, receive the Notions and Principles as Truth, and many of them worſhip under thoſe Forms and Notions, as in Spirit and Truth. The chief of moſt of them do joyn with them out of corrupt Ends, to be Head of the Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to exerciſe a kind of Domination, which is delightful to mankind: ſo that the Jeſuit doth no more than firſt diſtill a Poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonous Notion, and nurſe it, and defend it, till it be indifferent conſiderable: when accompliſhed, it will ſubſiſt of it ſelf, and put it ſelf into Form and Order. Then when he hath done that by Error, if that ſhould grow too faſt, he allayeth it, by ſubdivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of it by ſome true Notion, or ſome other erronious Notion, which are equally alike to the Jeſuit, for that the end of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign is, Dividing. When he hath devided and caſt a Nation into many and various Forms, he hath accompliſhed and arrived to his End; then, if he can Procure, Foment, or Stirr up Diſſatisfaction and Jealouſies betwixt the Intereſts, there he keepeth them in continual ebbing and flowing; and naturally every Perſwaſion will incline ſome to one Intereſt of State, ſome to another: As
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:107080:7"/>
for Example, the Epiſcopal doth naturally incline to a Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Campanella</hi> did give the King of <hi>Spain</hi> the beſt advice to practiſe this kind of Policy; yea, he commendeth it before the oppoſing of <hi>England</hi> by Arms. The reaſon why he choſe the Doctrine of Free-will to be firſt ſet on Foot in <hi>England,</hi> was, becauſe that Opinion concludeth Man to be a free Agent, which looſeneth and freeth the Diſciples thereof from more firm and founder Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and prepareth them to ſeek after new Lights; and when once arrived to this degree, immediately they turn <hi>Enthuſiaſts,</hi> who pretend, or think that all they do, is done by the Spirit, and that they are attended by the Spirit of Revelation: Our Quaker is much peſtered with the Malignant Influence of this Opinion.</p>
            <p>The Jeſuit, by this means, doth not only divide People, as to Religion, and thereby render them leſſe formidable againſt the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> but alſo, bringing an evil Report upon the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion, diſuniteth the affections of the Profeſſors there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and cauſeth Jealouſies, Heart-butnings, and Animoſities, One againſt the other; and taketh them off from the Power of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to defend Forms and Diſtinctions: and, that which is worſt of all, thereby increaſeth ſo many diſtinct and different Intereſts of State, as there are conſiderable perſwaſions in a Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth. When a Perſwaſion is grown up to be conſiderable, it giveth occaſion for Factions in State; Thereby, ſome ambitious men will become the Heads of this or that Faction, and by the Power of the Faction they Head, become Mighty.</p>
            <p>Now, if a State be led by ſuch Principles; W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at wickedneſs ſhall not it be led into? What Villanies ſhall not they attempt? What ſo Sacred, that they ſhall not Violate? Or, what Intereſt or Right will not they invade? What ſhall limit them, if they find opportunity to attempt the accompliſhing, or the attaining to their deſire? Miſerable is that Nation that is ſubject to ſuch In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniences; that are poyſoned with Opinions: The World is miſtaken, when they apprehend, that the Jeſuit worketh imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately in Councels to produce Turns and Changes of State; No but he worketh by remote Cauſes, ſuch as are here before pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed;
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:107080:7"/>
that is to ſay, by infuſing Notions deſtructive to publick ſafety, at firſt into the common People, then it is drunk in by great Ones, then it Cleaveth and Divideth a Nation into ſo many In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts as there are Perſwaſions; then he applyeth matter ſuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the Humor, and moſt apt to be received by the ſeveral Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions which ſhall work naturally ſuch Effects; and as it is the Policy of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> to preſerve it ſelf, by providing ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table entertainment for each Humor within it ſelf; ſo, it is to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy other Churches, by ſeveral Poyſons for each Humor.</p>
            <p>Therefore it behooveth all Chriſtian States to endeavour to fortifie themſelves with Union: When a State hath arrived to conſiſtency, its Form and Order, is a barr to the Jeſuits Operations. Thoſe States that are divided, have no means to ſtay themſelves from falling down the precipice of inevitable Ruine. The Jeſuit doth not only operate by diſtilling Notions in Religion, but alſo in affairs of State; as for Example, in the Caſe of our Controverſies between the Late King and the Parliament; the Parliament made Warr with Him, becauſe that the diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of the People did bear them up, and inabled them ſo to do; the which diſcontents were heightned by the Jeſuit. When the Warr was Ended, and the King overcome in the Field; it is evident, that the Jeſuit ſtirred up thoſe Sons of <hi>Belial</hi> to ſtain their Hands with his Sacred Blood; the Jeſuit alſo did practiſe and endeavour to incline the People to a Commonwealth: but in its Infancy alſo he endeavoured to ſtifle it, and prevent its ariving to a conſiſtency, leſt it ſhould be too firm and heavy for him to move. Alſo it is his deſign to endeavour the altering of a Commonwealth again into a Monarchy, and a Monarchy that is erected out of a Commonwealth into an Oligarchy; not that any one of the forms of Goverment will be more Subſervient to his deſign than any other, but that he may alwayes practiſe Changes: by which means a Proteſtant State is exerciſed with ſtrugling In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts within it ſelf, ſo that it ſhall be leſs formidable and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous to the Catholike States.</p>
            <p>That theſe things are not Conjectures, or taken up by ſuppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion onely, or that theſe and ſuch other Rules and Practiſes they
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:107080:8"/>
follow, is plainly demonſtrable by <hi>Adam Contzen</hi> the Jeſuit, in his Politick, <hi>Chap.</hi> 16, 17, 18.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Chap. 16.</bibl> Is to ſhew that Princes muſt determine of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in Religion; as having power to defend that which the Pope determineth of, but no power to appoint or change any thing themſelves, or judge of Controverſies. The Church muſt Judge, and the Prince muſt Execute.</q>
            <p>Take notice that one of their Maxims is, that the Magiſtrate hath nothing to do with matters of Religion. As that Maxim ſerveth their purpoſe to ſtrengthen the Power of the Chruch, and weaken that of the Magiſtrate in Catholike-States. So it ſerveth their purpoſe in Proteſtant States to weaken the Magiſtrate, and lay all in confuſion in the Church.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Chap. 17.</bibl> Is to ſhew, That to preſerve Religion, (that is Popery), no other Religion ſhould be permitted: <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ut it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>: of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>tch of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> to Cry <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ll To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ion, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Policy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ined <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Power.</note> and that Riches tend much to ſtrengthen the Clergy, and preſerve Religion; and <hi>the poverty of the Proteſtant Miniſters</hi> (which muſt be by all means endeavoured).</q>
            <p>As he here preſcribeth means to inrich the Popiſh Miniſtery, he adviſeth the impoveriſhing the Proteſtant, that they may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come diſabled and diſcouraged to ſtudy and labour in the Work of the Miniſtery, as alſo that by poverty they may become con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible: Indeed the Proteſtant-Miniſter is an Eye-ſore to the Catholike; and thoſe that Cry out againſt Miniſters maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, do nothing elſe than the work of the Jeſuit.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Chap. 18.</bibl> To bring in Popery, and aboliſh the Proteſtants Religion, is, to make uſe of the Proteſtants Contentions. How eaſie is it <hi>(ſaith he)</hi> in <hi>England</hi> to bring the Puritans into Order, if they be forced to approve Biſhops? or to reduce the Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans in the Low Countries, if the Prince adhere to the <hi>Armi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians?</hi> For the Variety of Opinions makes that doubtful, that before ſeemed certain; ſo that the when Magiſtrate joyneth with one ſide, he eaſily overtuns the other, and leaves the whole obnoxious: As <hi>Paul</hi> did by the diſſenſion between the Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees and Sadduces; joyning to one ſide, he eſcaped. This <hi>(ſaith he)</hi> I would principally perſwade an Orthodox Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:107080:8"/>
to <hi>(that is, a Papiſt.)</hi> For he may with as much advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage make uſe of the Proteſtants diſagreements, as of the Papiſts Concord, to extirpate Proteſtants. As in Warrs, it is not onely the skill and ſtrength of the General, but often alſo the Careleſneſs of the Enemy, or his Miſtake, that gives very great advantages for ſucceſſe. When rigid <hi>Calviniſm</hi> was aſſaulted by the <hi>Lutherans,</hi> in the heat of the Paroxyſm, it was exaſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and the ſuddain reſtraint did much hurt: But now the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minians</hi> have of their own accord let go the hardeſt part of their rigor, and judge the <hi>Calviniſts</hi> to be impious, and perſecute them in the very Univerſities, and in other Towns they force them to baniſhment: and would venture to do more and cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler things, if they were not afraid of the ſtrength of the adverſe Party.</q>
            <p>That he here ſaith of Contentions, is ſufficiently practiſed: Firſt, To Create them; And Secondly, To Foment them. That which <hi>Contzen</hi> principally taketh notice of, is, That Order in the Puritans or Profeſſors of Religion in <hi>England,</hi> is eaſy to be ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected: But he adviſeth, that the Magiſtrate, or Agent for the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> do make uſe of the Proteſtants differences, and not permit them to Unite; but rather perſue all Wayes and Means of contriving Diſ-union, fomenting of Breaches amongſt the Profeſſors of Religion of all ſorts, and more eſpecially the Church and State of <hi>England,</hi> than any other; for that it is the greateſt State or Kingdom that is in Europ, that is freed from the Barbarous and Intolerable Yoke of the Papal Soveraignty or Supremacy; it is a Place whence the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath been plentifully ſupplyed with vaſt ſums impoſed upon this Kingdom, and obtainted from it: It is evident, that what is here afferted, is no leſs than Truth; and it behooveth all Intereſts and Perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to reconcil to, conform and unite, and decline being Authors of Diſcord in the Church: Certain it is, That that which muſt be able to ſtand like a Rock againſt the violent and open Force of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and its private undermining Policies muſt be ſomething elſe then general Indulgence; He who hath any reaſon, and hath obſerved any thing of the Practice and Policy of the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:107080:9"/>
Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> muſt conclude, that it muſt be Union under a well-governed Church, that muſt be managed by Councell that muſt be careful of making good their Ground, and be able to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect their Policies and new Contrivances.</p>
            <p>I ſhall add one thing more of <hi>Campanella,</hi> Chap. 18. <hi>Advice to the King of</hi> Spain.</p>
            <p>Neither would I have this one thing to be omitted; namely, that He erect certain Colledges through all the Provinces of his Dominions, in which ſhould be placed all the moſt Ingenious Boyes of the ſaid Provinces; (and who are ſuch, may eaſily be known, by their firſt Maſters, that taught them their Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, and other the Firſt Rudiments) and theſe, being thus culled out of all Grammer-Schools, I would have to be brought up, and maintained at the Kings Charge; and there ſhould be a <hi>New Order</hi> ſet up of them, like that of St. <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minick;</hi> which <hi>Order</hi> I would have called, The <hi>Auſtrian Order.</hi> And when any of theſe were come to be 18 years old, they ſhould then be commanded to Preach: and theſe I would have to be called, <hi>The Kings Preachers;</hi> and they ſhould then be ſent abroad, ſome into <hi>Germany,</hi> and others into <hi>England:</hi> where, if they have managed their buſineſs rightly, and well; at their return they ſhould have Biſhop-ricks conferted upon them by the King, of thoſe that are in the Kings own Gift: for, by ſo doing, he ſhall render himſelf ſecure, both from the Pope, and alſo againſt all perfidious Preachers and Hereticks; and by this means ſuch perſons only ſhall be maintained at His Charge, as do him ſervice for it, and advance His affairs.</p>
            <p>This is an evident Demonſtration of the Practiſes of the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> and it would not be amiſs, if that ſomething of the like nature were undertaken for the Church and State of <hi>England.</hi> Chelſey-Colledge Erected, might be of uſe, and become a good Expedient againſt the underminings of the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> the Hinderers of that Work, were no Friends to the Church of <hi>England.</hi> How far any can be deemed a Friend to Church or State that is a Roman Catholick, is a great Queſtion: For that all Pretences, Oaths, Abjurations (what not?) in their Opinion may be abſolved by the Pope: If ſo, what can a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Prince or State expect from them? they may be Friends to Him in a degree, leſs or more, as their Intereſt ſhall lead them, and not otherwiſe.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
